<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<author>Martijn Dashorst</author>
		<title>Building jWebunit</title>
	</properties>
<body class="default">
<section name="Building jWebUnit with Maven">
	<p>
		Maven is, just like ant, a build tool. However, where you have to tell ant what it
		needs to do and how, you only have to tell Maven what you need, if you adhere to the
		Maven standards.
	</p>
	<p>
		In order to use Maven to build jWebUnit, you need to have Maven installed. This should
		not be any more difficult than installing ant. We've included a best practise installation
		and configuration for Maven.
	</p>
<subsection name="Installing Maven">
	<p>
		First you need to download the latest Maven, which currently is <tt>Maven-1.0-rc3</tt> 
		(release candidate 3), make sure you download the archive (zip), not the exe installer.
	</p>
	<p>
		Installing Maven should be easy: unzip the file to any directory you like, let's say: 
		<source>c:\Maven-1.0-rc3</source>
	</p>
	<p>
		Next you need to do 3 things:
		<ul>
			<li>add an environment variable MAVEN_HOME which points to the install directory of Maven, i.e. C:\maven-1.0-rc3</li>
			<li>add <tt>%MAVEN_HOME%\bin</tt> to your path (using the variable you can switch more easily when a new version arrives)</li>
			<li>add to your home directory (under windows 2000 and XP: C:\Documents and Settings\username) a file called build.properties, and
		and put the following entries in it:
		<table>
			<tr><th>entry</th><th>description</th></tr>
			<tr><td>maven.home.local=${maven.home}/cache</td><td>The directory where Maven installs the plugins.</td></tr>
			<tr><td>maven.repo.local=c:/maven-repository</td><td>The directory where Maven downloads dependencies of your project (jars)</td></tr>
			<tr><td>maven.repo.remote=http://www.ibiblio.org/maven</td><td>The URL where Maven can download the dependencies from (comma seperated for multiple entries).</td></tr>
		</table>
		</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>
		You can replace the <tt>maven.repo.local</tt> entry with a directory of your liking. 
		I advise you to make the directory seperate from the Maven home directory. 
		Maven downloads all dependencies into this directory. This repository can 
		be shared among different Maven versions and even developers on the same machine. 
		The cache directory (the first entry) can't be shared between Maven versions, 
		so this should stay within the Maven home directory.
	</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Using Maven">
	<p>
		Maven defines several goals, depending on the plugins you've installed, for
		creating and building your application. A goal is similar to an Ant-task. For
		instance: to compile the java sources one could do:
		<source>maven java:compile</source>
		Also, a goal can depend on other goals: the <tt>jar:jar</tt> goal depends on
		running the unit tests and compilation of the code.
	</p>
	<p>
		See the <a href="http://maven.apache.org">Maven site</a> for more information 
		on the different goals and plugins that are available.
	</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Building jWebUnit">
	<p>
		Building jWebUnit merely consist of running Maven:
		<source>maven</source>
		If you run Maven from a fresh install and you configured Maven as described
		earlier, you will see (an english version of) the following text:
<source><![CDATA[
 __  __
|  \/  |__ _Apache__ ___
| |\/| / _` \ V / -_) ' \  ~ intelligent projects ~
|_|  |_\__,_|\_/\___|_||_|  v. 1.0-rc3

Plugin cache will be regenerated
Directory c:\maven-repository bestaat niet. Probeer hem aan te maken.
Probeer junit-3.8.1.jar te downloaden.
........
Probeer nekohtml-0.8.1.jar te downloaden.
....
Probeer js-1.5R4.1.jar te downloaden.
.......................
Probeer xml-apis-1.0.b2.jar te downloaden.
.....
Probeer xercesImpl-2.6.2.jar te downloaden.
....................................
Probeer servletapi-2.3.jar te downloaden.
...
Probeer httpunit-1.5.4.jar te downloaden.
...............
Probeer dom4j-1.4-dev-8.jar te downloaden.
.....................

<- <- <- <- SNIP -> -> -> ->

build:start:

java:prepare-filesystem:

java:compile:
    [echo] Compiling to C:\workspace\jWebUnit/target/classes

java:jar-resources:

test:prepare-filesystem:

test:test-resources:

test:compile:

test:test:
    [junit] Running net.sourceforge.jwebunit.ExpectedTableAssertionsTest
    [junit] Tests run: 2, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Time elapsed: 0,594 sec
    [junit] Running net.sourceforge.jwebunit.ExpectedTableTest
    [junit] Tests run: 4, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Time elapsed: 0,343 sec
<- <- <- <- SNIP -> -> -> ->
    [junit] Running net.sourceforge.jwebunit.WebCookieTest
    [junit] Tests run: 1, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Time elapsed: 0,422 sec

jar:jar:
    [echo] Warning: shortDescription is greater than 49 characters - trimming for specification title.
    [jar] Building jar: C:\workspace\jWebUnit\target\jwebunit-1.2.jar
BUILD SUCCESSFUL
Total time: 1 minutes 53 seconds
Finished at: Mon Jun 07 23:06:15 CEST 2004
]]></source></p>
	<p>
		You now have successfully built the <tt>jWebUnit.jar</tt>.
	</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Building the site">
	<p>
		Generating the jWebUnit website with maven is also not difficult:
		<source>maven site</source>
		is all there's to it.
		After downloading lots and lots of jar files, maven will build the website which 
		contains junit results, checkstyle results, and the like, just like the website
		you're now looking at. You can find the website in the 
		<source>target/docs</source> directory.
	</p>
	<p>
		Just open the index.html in your browser.
	</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Building a release">
	<p>
		Building a release with maven consists of executing Maven like this:
		<source>maven dist</source>
		This will create the binary and source distributions in the directory
		<source>target/distributions</source>
		In the jWebUnit case, only the binary release is relevant, as it includes
		the full source in order to build maven oneself.
	</p>
	<p>
		Distribution of the release is not automated. In the <tt>project.xml</tt>
		my local linux machine is used to test the distribution. This will change
		in the near future to use the sourceforge filesystems.
	</p>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>