<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="dashorst.at.users.sourceforge.net">Martijn Dashorst</author>
        <title>JWebUnit 1.x</title>
    </properties>
    <meta name="keyword" content="jwebunit, java, junit, htmlunit, jacobie, httpunit, integration, test, automated, html, webtest"/>
	<head>
		<link rel="shortcut icon" href="favicon.ico" type="image/x-icon" />
	</head>
<body>
<section name="Welcome">
    <p>
        You are on the JWebUnit 1.x website. Current version is 1.4-RC3. This is
        the "stable" version of JWebUnit. You can also consult <a href="2.x/index.html">JWebUnit 2.x website</a>.
    </p>
</section>
<section name="What is JWebUnit?">
    <p>
        JWebUnit is a Java framework that facilitates creation of acceptance tests for web applications. It 
        evolved from a project where we were using <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit</a> to create acceptance tests. 
        Also, we can have different testing engines. Currently, only <a href="jwebunit-htmlunit-plugin/index.html">HtmlUnit plugin</a> is ready.
        As the tests were being written, they were continuously refactored to remove duplication and other bad smells in the test 
        code. JWebUnit is the result of these refactorings.
    </p>
</section>
<section name="What does JWebUnit provide?">
    <p>
        JWebUnit provides a high-level API for navigating a web application combined with a set
        of assertions to verify the application's correctness. This includes navigation
        via links, form entry and submission, validation of table contents, and other
        typical business web application features. This code try to stay independent of the libraries behind
        the scenes. The simple navigation methods and ready-to-use assertions allow for
        more rapid test creation than using only JUnit and HtmlUnit. And if you want to switch
        from HtmlUnit to the other soon available plugins, no need to rewrite your tests.
    </p>
    <img src="images/jwebunit-architecture.png" alt="JWebUnit architecture"/>
</section>
</body>    
</document>
