<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="dashorst.at.users.sourceforge.net">Martijn Dashorst</author>
        <title>jWebUnit</title>
    </properties>
    <meta name="keyword" content="jwebunit, java, junit, httpunit, integration, test, automated, html, webtest"/>
	<head>
		<link rel="shortcut icon" href="favicon.ico" type="image/x-icon" />
	</head>
<body>
<section name="What is jWebUnit?">
    <p>
        jWebUnit is a Java framework that facilitates creation of acceptance tests for web applications. It 
        evolved from a project where we were using <a href="http://www.junit.org">JUnit</a> to create acceptance tests. 
        Also, we have two testing engines <a href="http://httpunit.sourceforge.net/">HttpUnit</a> and <a href="http://jacobie.sourceforge.net/">Jacobie</a>. 
        As the tests were being written, they were continuously refactored to remove duplication and other bad smells in the test 
        code. jWebUnit is the result of these refactorings.
    </p>
</section>
<section name="Now integrated with Jacobie (testing engine)!!!!">
    <p>
        jWebUnit is a pround to finally announce the new feature of testing engines within jWebUnit.  The traditional
        testing engine is httpunit.  The second testing engine is jacobie.  Jacobie is a java-based internet explorer
        wrapper.  This will allow you to use the same code or test scripts and visually run the tests.  Plus, if you
        run the tests in debug, you can pause (breakpoint), and then add other information into the form, etc.  We
        hope you enjoy this new feature after about a year of work, it has finally came to reality.
    </p>
</section>
<section name="What does jWebUnit provide?">
    <p>
        jWebUnit provides a high-level API for navigating a web application combined with a set
        of assertions to verify the application's correctness. This includes navigation
        via links, form entry and submission, validation of table contents, and other
        typical business web application features. This code utilizes HttpUnit behind
        the scenes. The simple navigation methods and ready-to-use assertions allow for
        more rapid test creation than using only JUnit and HttpUnit.
    </p>
    <p>
        The following sample testcases illustrate the conciseness of jWebUnit versus HttpUnit
        and JUnit alone.  The tests perform a google search
        for the HttpUnit home page, navigate to that page from Google, and validate that
        there is a link to the user manual on the HttpUnit home page.  The code in the
        first column is pure HttpUnit / JUnit, while the second column uses the jWebUnit framework.
    </p>
    <p>
<table cellspacing="2" border="0">
<tr><th>JUnit/HttpUnit Test</th><th>jWebUnit Test</th></tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" nowrap="nowrap">
<source>
package net.sourceforge.jwebunit.sample;

import junit.framework.TestCase;
import com.meterware.httpunit.WebResponse;
import com.meterware.httpunit.WebConversation;
import com.meterware.httpunit.WebForm;
import com.meterware.httpunit.WebRequest;

public class SearchExample extends TestCase {

   public void testSearch() throws Exception {
      WebConversation wc = new WebConversation();
      WebResponse resp = wc.getResponse( "http://www.google.com");
      WebForm form = resp.getForms()[0];
      form.setParameter("q", "HttpUnit");
      WebRequest req = form.getRequest("btnG");
      resp = wc.getResponse(req);
      assertNotNull(resp.getLinkWith("HttpUnit"));
      resp = resp.getLinkWith("HttpUnit").click();
      assertEquals(resp.getTitle(), "HttpUnit");
      assertNotNull(resp.getLinkWith("User's Manual"));
   }
}
</source>
</td>
<td valign="top" nowrap="nowrap">
<source>
package net.sourceforge.jwebunit.sample;

import net.sourceforge.jwebunit.WebTestCase;

public class JWebUnitSearchExample extends WebTestCase {

   public JWebUnitSearchExample(String name) {
      super(name);
   }

   public void setUp() {
      getTestContext().setBaseUrl("http://www.google.com");
   }

   public void testSearch() {
      beginAt("/");
      setFormElement("q", "httpunit");
      submit("btnG");
      clickLinkWithText("HttpUnit");
      assertTitleEquals("HttpUnit");
      assertLinkPresentWithText("User's Manual");
   }
}
</source>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</p>
</section>
</body>    
</document>
